<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://bonelab.ca/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://bonelab.ca/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-08-23T02:35:14+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bone Imaging Laboratory</title><entry><title type="html">Extraction of an image mask from polygon data</title><link href="https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/22/masks-from-polygon-data.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Extraction of an image mask from polygon data" /><published>2024-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-23T02:33:57+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/22/masks-from-polygon-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/22/masks-from-polygon-data.html"><![CDATA[<p>Cortical bone mapping with global optimization produces incredible results for all types
of CT data, including clinical CT and HR-pQCT. The result of the algorithm is a polygon
dataset of the periosteal surface of the bone and scalars representing the local thickness
(i.e., periosteal to endosteal) calculated by the algorithm. The calculation of cortical
thickness can be summarized from the individual data points (i.e., means, standard deviations,
localized measurements, etc).</p>

<p>https://github.com/Bonelab/Bonelab/blob/master/bonelab/cli/treece_thickness.py</p>

<p>However, the algorithm cannot produce an image mask. So the aim of this project is to develop 
additional functionality that outputs a binarized image with voxels labelled as cortical bone (127), 
trabecular bone (100), and background (0). The image will be the identical size to the input
that is input. Likely it would be based on VTK stencil objects (similar to blRapidPrototype):</p>

<p>https://github.com/Bonelab/Bonelab/blob/master/bonelab/cli/RapidPrototype.py</p>

<p>When completed it will be validated on HR-pQCT of radius, tibia and knee, as well as QCT of 
abdomen and knee.</p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Boyd</name></author><category term="software" /><category term="image processing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cortical bone mapping with global optimization produces incredible results for all types of CT data, including clinical CT and HR-pQCT. The result of the algorithm is a polygon dataset of the periosteal surface of the bone and scalars representing the local thickness (i.e., periosteal to endosteal) calculated by the algorithm. The calculation of cortical thickness can be summarized from the individual data points (i.e., means, standard deviations, localized measurements, etc).]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/Treece.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/Treece.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Determine the limits of the association between bone mineral density and bone strength</title><link href="https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/20/bmd-to-strength-relationship.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Determine the limits of the association between bone mineral density and bone strength" /><published>2024-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-23T02:33:57+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/20/bmd-to-strength-relationship</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/20/bmd-to-strength-relationship.html"><![CDATA[<p>There is a strong relationship between bone mineral density (BMD) and bone strength, however
that relationship breaks down when bone microarchitecture is affected. It is difficult to know
the relative roles of BMD and bone microarchitecture to estimated bone strength. But, with our
TBONE project we have a unique opportunity to find a relationship between BMD and strength
before space flight, immediately upon return to Earth, and a year after recovery. Although BMD
recovers, the bone microarchitecture may be forever altered. We can test that relationship with
this unique dataset.</p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Boyd</name></author><category term="finite elements" /><category term="bone density" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There is a strong relationship between bone mineral density (BMD) and bone strength, however that relationship breaks down when bone microarchitecture is affected. It is difficult to know the relative roles of BMD and bone microarchitecture to estimated bone strength. But, with our TBONE project we have a unique opportunity to find a relationship between BMD and strength before space flight, immediately upon return to Earth, and a year after recovery. Although BMD recovers, the bone microarchitecture may be forever altered. We can test that relationship with this unique dataset.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/Numerics88.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/Numerics88.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Opportunistic detection and risk assessment of vertebral fractures in high-risk populations using machine learning</title><link href="https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/19/vertebral-fractures.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opportunistic detection and risk assessment of vertebral fractures in high-risk populations using machine learning" /><published>2024-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-23T02:33:57+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/19/vertebral-fractures</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/19/vertebral-fractures.html"><![CDATA[<p>Training a machine learning model that can identify vertebral fractures in clinical CT scans. 
This model could either identify the presence of fractures OR identify the fractures and give 
the fracture a grade based on Genant classification. Once the ML model is developed, it could 
be used on RETRO2 to create associations with fracture risk and individuals with various spinal 
conditions (Schmorl’s Nodes, Ankylosing Spondylitis, Diffuse Idiopathic Skeletal Hyperostosis, etc.). 
Or could be integrated into the entire opportunistic CT pipeline, since clinicians would be 
interested in finding ways to identify fractures opportunistically.</p>]]></content><author><name>Bryn Matheson</name></author><category term="machine learning" /><category term="clinical ct" /><category term="fracture" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Training a machine learning model that can identify vertebral fractures in clinical CT scans. This model could either identify the presence of fractures OR identify the fractures and give the fracture a grade based on Genant classification. Once the ML model is developed, it could be used on RETRO2 to create associations with fracture risk and individuals with various spinal conditions (Schmorl’s Nodes, Ankylosing Spondylitis, Diffuse Idiopathic Skeletal Hyperostosis, etc.). Or could be integrated into the entire opportunistic CT pipeline, since clinicians would be interested in finding ways to identify fractures opportunistically.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/Opportunistic.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/Opportunistic.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>