<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://bonelab.ca/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://bonelab.ca/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-08-15T00:38:48+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bone Imaging Laboratory</title><entry><title type="html">A comparison of asynchronous to synchronous calibration</title><link href="https://bonelab.ca/2025/04/25/asynchronous-calibration.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A comparison of asynchronous to synchronous calibration" /><published>2025-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-15T00:29:02+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/2025/04/25/asynchronous-calibration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bonelab.ca/2025/04/25/asynchronous-calibration.html"><![CDATA[<p>Does synchronous calibration work as well as we think?</p>

<p>Typically CT scans are not acquired with a calibration phantom in the scan (i.e., synchronous calibration) and so we have to either perform internal calibration or use synchronous calibration (i.e., scan the phantom in the same scanner as the patient, but not at the same time). The reason a phantom is not used clinically is because most CT imaging is not quantitative, but rather used for diagnostic purposes. We assume that the best way to have quantitative data is to include a calibration phantom, but is it? Does the inclusion of the dense phantom rods actually lead to beam hardening that alters the resulting BMD? This is hard to know because it’d require scanning a person twice: once with the phantom and once without the phantom (and them scan the phantom separately).</p>

<p>This project would propose to test whether an in-scan phantom results in the most accurate quantitative CT outcome. We would work with the gross anatomy lab to scan a fresh cadaver with and without the calibration phantom in place. We would do this for a KUB scan as well as a chest scan. Although BMD is our ultimate outcome of interest, our comparison would be based on the HU from each scan. Using ML we’d segment the L1-L4 and left/right femurs and calculate the mean HU in each bone.</p>

<p>Additional measures we might consider are adjusting table height as well as employing internal calibration. Since it is a lot of work to have a cadaver in the scanner we might consider other scanning protocols as well (i.e., knees, head).</p>

<p>Image shown is from Mateo Ruedes.</p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Boyd</name></author><category term="clinical ct" /><category term="image processing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Does synchronous calibration work as well as we think?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/asynchronous.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/asynchronous.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Using machine learning for feature detection and extraction from MRI</title><link href="https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/29/mri-machine-learning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using machine learning for feature detection and extraction from MRI" /><published>2024-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-15T00:29:02+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/29/mri-machine-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/29/mri-machine-learning.html"><![CDATA[<p>Training machine learning models for the extraction of several features from different MRI sequences…</p>

<p>From PD sequences, we can detect/extract bone, cartilage, and meniscus tears.
From T2 sequences, we can detect/extract bone, bone marrow lesions (BMLs), and cartilage. This project
would build on our previous work:</p>

<p><em>Stirling CE, Neeteson NJ, Walker REA, Boyd SK, 2024. Deep learning-based automated detection and segmentation of bone and traumatic bone marrow lesions from MRI following an acute ACL tear. Computers in Biology and Medicine 178, 108791.</em></p>

<p>A model to segment the meniscus could be developed and then compared to our surgical reports from the 
SALTAC and SALTACII studies.</p>]]></content><author><name>Callie Stirling</name></author><category term="mri" /><category term="machine-learning" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Training machine learning models for the extraction of several features from different MRI sequences…]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/bml.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/bml.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Prevalence of Patellar Osteoarthritis Following ACL Injury</title><link href="https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/29/patella-oa.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Prevalence of Patellar Osteoarthritis Following ACL Injury" /><published>2024-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-15T00:29:02+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/29/patella-oa</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/29/patella-oa.html"><![CDATA[<p>Can we see signs of osteoarthritis in the patella?</p>

<p>Post-traumatic osteoarthritis (PTOA) is a common long-term consequence of anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) injuries. The prevalence of patellofemoral joint (PFJ) osteoarthritis (OA) after ACL injury varies widely across studies. Historically, more attention has been given to the tibiofemoral joint due to its primary role in weight-bearing and the more obvious biomechanical changes post-ACL injury. Patellofemoral OA can be more difficult to diagnose and quantify, especially in the early stages, compared to tibiofemoral OA.</p>

<p>This project proposes to investigate the development and progression of PFJ OA by examining changes in bone microarchitecture in the patella following ACL injuries. Specifically, it focuses on characterizing alterations in the microstructural properties of subchondral bone post-ACL injury and assessing the relationship between these bone changes and OA progression over time.</p>]]></content><author><name>Callie Stirling</name></author><category term="hr-pqct" /><category term="image processing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Can we see signs of osteoarthritis in the patella?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/patella.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/patella.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring µFRAC and the relevance of skeletal sites</title><link href="https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/25/alternative-uFRAC-models.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring µFRAC and the relevance of skeletal sites" /><published>2024-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-15T00:29:02+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/25/alternative-uFRAC-models</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/25/alternative-uFRAC-models.html"><![CDATA[<p>Can we predict fragility fractures using only one skeletal site instead of two…</p>

<p>The fracture prediction tool called µFRAC was designed to take HR-pQCT data of the radius 
and tibia combined with finite element analysis and femoral neck DXA (with some clinical factors)
and estimate 5-year and 10-year fracture risk of MOF and AOF. Do we really need to include both
the radius and tibia? The tibia is representative of a weight-bearing bone and is highly correlated
to the bone strength at the spine and hip, whereas the radius seems to capture features of aging
such as deteriorated architecture (e.g., void spaces). It is not clear whether a simpler version of
µFRAC would perform as well, but if it did that would make its use more versatile. This study would
explore µFRAC based on tibia alone, radius alone, and perhaps even bi-lateral tibia and/or bi-lateral
radius scans. This study builds on the establishment of µFRAC as an alternative to FRAX+DXA for fragility
fracture screening or provide a strong complementary option for when FRAX+DXA is provides a somewhat 
ambiguous clinicial treatment decisions basis.</p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Boyd, with Danielle Whittier</name></author><category term="hr-pqct" /><category term="fracture risk" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Can we predict fragility fractures using only one skeletal site instead of two…]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/ufrac.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/ufrac.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Making research data available for Open Science</title><link href="https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/07/preparation-open-science-data.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making research data available for Open Science" /><published>2024-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-15T00:29:02+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/07/preparation-open-science-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/07/preparation-open-science-data.html"><![CDATA[<p>Taking the leap to making large datasets available for Open Science…</p>

<p>This project is aimed at supporting the concepts of Open Science. We have accrued numerous
datasets in the Bone Imaging Laboratory that would be valuable to the general scientific 
community. Although the process of making data available via Open Science, there are several
challenges that need to be resolved. This include aspects such as (a) ensuring anonymity of the
data, (b) consent to share the data, (c) establishing a place to share the data (i.e., Zenodo),
(d) formatting the data and meta-data such that it follows a standard (i.e., BIDS) by implementing
new MIDS (linked at https://www.ormir.org), (e) setting up permissions for sharing, (f) instructions
on how to cite the data (i.e., https://zenodo.org and/or https://www.nature.com/sdata/). I’m sure
there are many other considerations.</p>

<p>We could explore this process by using a complex dataset such as the Vitamin D study, which includes
HR-pQCT, DXA, biomarker, etc. Or we could start with a simpler dataset, such as ARTININ, which
includes only clinical CT data.</p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Boyd</name></author><category term="hr-pqct" /><category term="clinical CT" /><category term="mri" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Taking the leap to making large datasets available for Open Science…]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/openscienceideas.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/openscienceideas.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Improved image segmentation of bone by image filtering</title><link href="https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/06/improving-trabecular-segmentation-by-image-filtering.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Improved image segmentation of bone by image filtering" /><published>2024-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-15T00:29:02+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/06/improving-trabecular-segmentation-by-image-filtering</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bonelab.ca/2024/10/06/improving-trabecular-segmentation-by-image-filtering.html"><![CDATA[<p>Can we do a better job of segmenting the trabecular structure in knee scans by HR-pQCT…</p>

<p>The use of HR-pQCT of the knee is relatively new, and although we are able to collect images
as part of our normal protocol now, the size of the knee seems to lead to some beam hardening 
issues at the centre. This is manifested as a slight darking of the trabecular structure. There
is work by the UCSF group (Kazakia, Burghardt) that has shown the so-called Laplace-Hamming
filter provided by Scanco Medical IPL seems to perform better than the standard Gaussian filtering.
Other methods such as Otsu’s method, adaptive filtering, etc, are also options.</p>

<p>The goal of this project is to compare filtering methods on the ability to extract bone 
microarchitecture. We would want to determine how these affect measures such as TbTh and TbSp, 
and possibly finite element outcomes. This could be explored using the TRIKNEE study where we
have three repeat measures on the same individual for a small cohort. The ground-truth would be
taken as the Gauss segmentation, since we don’t have a true gold standard for these in vivo scans.</p>

<p>We have implemented a L-H filter here: https://github.com/Bonelab/Bonelab/blob/master/bonelab%2Fcli%2Ffft_laplace_hamming.py</p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Boyd, with Nathan Neeteson</name></author><category term="hr-pqct" /><category term="image processing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Can we do a better job of segmenting the trabecular structure in knee scans by HR-pQCT…]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/kneeinprofile.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/kneeinprofile.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Establishing the fibular as a non-weight bearing control</title><link href="https://bonelab.ca/2024/09/29/establish-fibular-as-nonweightbearing-control.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Establishing the fibular as a non-weight bearing control" /><published>2024-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-15T00:29:02+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/2024/09/29/establish-fibular-as-nonweightbearing-control</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bonelab.ca/2024/09/29/establish-fibular-as-nonweightbearing-control.html"><![CDATA[<p>Establishing whether the fibula can be a non-weight bearing control instead of distal radius…</p>

<p>We know that typically the two main HR-pQCT scanning sites, the radius and tibia, often are 
surrogates for non-weight bearing and weight-bearing mechanical loading, respectively. However,
a complicating factor of the radius is that it is also a site that is prone to motion artifact
during HR-pQCT acquisition. There is research showing that the fibula is not carrying very much
weight relative to the tibia, and since it is scanned in the same FOV as the tibia, it is
subject to exactly the same motion artifacts. Therefore, to determine whether a mechanical 
stimulus, such as microgravity induced bone loss in space flight, it would be possible to 
confirm this difference more clearly because it removes the confounding effect of the motion 
differences between tibia and radius.</p>

<p>It would require going back to the original ISQ files from the TBONE study and extracting the 
fibula from each scan. This would involve a simple modification to the IPL script that gets the
“largest bone” to getting the “second largest bone”. Subsequently, a full morphological analysis
and voxel-based assessment could be performed on the fibula data for direct comparison to the 
tibia.</p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Boyd, with Matthias Walle</name></author><category term="hr-pqct" /><category term="image processing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Establishing whether the fibula can be a non-weight bearing control instead of distal radius…]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/TBONE.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/TBONE.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Extraction of an image mask from polygon data</title><link href="https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/22/masks-from-polygon-data.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Extraction of an image mask from polygon data" /><published>2024-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-15T00:29:02+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/22/masks-from-polygon-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/22/masks-from-polygon-data.html"><![CDATA[<p>Developing a new method with universal application for defining bone compartments…</p>

<p>Cortical bone mapping with global optimization produces incredible results for all types
of CT data, including clinical CT and HR-pQCT. The result of the algorithm is a polygon
dataset of the periosteal surface of the bone and scalars representing the local thickness
(i.e., periosteal to endosteal) calculated by the algorithm. The calculation of cortical
thickness can be summarized from the individual data points (i.e., means, standard deviations,
localized measurements, etc).</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/Bonelab/Bonelab/blob/master/bonelab/cli/treece_thickness.py">https://github.com/Bonelab/Bonelab/blob/master/bonelab/cli/treece_thickness.py</a></p>

<p>However, the algorithm cannot produce an image mask. So the aim of this project is to develop 
additional functionality that outputs a binarized image with voxels labelled as cortical bone (127), 
trabecular bone (100), and background (0). The image will be the identical size to the input
that is input. Likely it would be based on VTK stencil objects (similar to blRapidPrototype):</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/Bonelab/Bonelab/blob/master/bonelab/cli/RapidPrototype.py">https://github.com/Bonelab/Bonelab/blob/master/bonelab/cli/RapidPrototype.py</a></p>

<p>When completed it will be validated on HR-pQCT of radius, tibia and knee, as well as QCT of 
abdomen and knee.</p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Boyd</name></author><category term="software" /><category term="image processing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Developing a new method with universal application for defining bone compartments…]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/Treece.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/Treece.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Determine the limits of the association between bone mineral density and bone strength</title><link href="https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/20/bmd-to-strength-relationship.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Determine the limits of the association between bone mineral density and bone strength" /><published>2024-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-15T00:29:02+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/20/bmd-to-strength-relationship</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/20/bmd-to-strength-relationship.html"><![CDATA[<p>Exploring the relationship between BMD and bone strength: can microarchitecture break the link?</p>

<p>There is a strong relationship between bone mineral density (BMD) and bone strength, however
that relationship breaks down when bone microarchitecture is affected. It is difficult to know
the relative roles of BMD and bone microarchitecture to estimated bone strength. But, with our
TBONE project we have a unique opportunity to find a relationship between BMD and strength
before space flight, immediately upon return to Earth, and a year after recovery. Although BMD
recovers, the bone microarchitecture may be forever altered. We can test that relationship with
this unique dataset.</p>]]></content><author><name>Steven Boyd</name></author><category term="finite elements" /><category term="bone density" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring the relationship between BMD and bone strength: can microarchitecture break the link?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/Numerics88.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/Numerics88.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Opportunistic detection and risk assessment of vertebral fractures in high-risk populations using machine learning</title><link href="https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/19/vertebral-fractures.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opportunistic detection and risk assessment of vertebral fractures in high-risk populations using machine learning" /><published>2024-08-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-15T00:29:02+00:00</updated><id>https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/19/vertebral-fractures</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bonelab.ca/2024/08/19/vertebral-fractures.html"><![CDATA[<p>Training a machine learning model that can identify vertebral fractures in clinical CT scans…</p>

<p>Training a machine learning model that can identify vertebral fractures in clinical CT scans.
This model could either identify the presence of fractures OR identify the fractures and give 
the fracture a grade based on Genant classification. Once the ML model is developed, it could 
be used on RETRO2 to create associations with fracture risk and individuals with various spinal 
conditions (Schmorl’s Nodes, Ankylosing Spondylitis, Diffuse Idiopathic Skeletal Hyperostosis, etc.). 
Or could be integrated into the entire opportunistic CT pipeline, since clinicians would be 
interested in finding ways to identify fractures opportunistically.</p>]]></content><author><name>Bryn Matheson</name></author><category term="machine learning" /><category term="clinical ct" /><category term="fracture" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Training a machine learning model that can identify vertebral fractures in clinical CT scans…]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/Opportunistic.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://bonelab.ca/images/projects/Opportunistic.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>